Guide to the Larry Neal papers
New York Public Library
Larry Neal papers
1961-1985
Sc MG 344
20745
Neal, Larry, 1937-
New York Public Library Stephen A. Schwarzman Building Fifth Avenue at 42nd Street New York, NY 10018-2788
16.8 linear feet (45 boxes)
The Larry Neal Papers document his role as a writer/editor and seminal figure in the Black Arts Movement, and consists principally of Neal's diverse forms of writings, including essays, scripts, screenplays, poems, short stories and anthologies. Published copies of some of his writings are included in the collection, as are writings by colleagues and publishers.
Larry (Lawrence Paul) Neal was well-known as a writer, literary and music critic, and major catalyst for the Black Arts Movement of the 1960's and 1970's. Born September 5, 1937 in Atlanta, Georgia he grew up in Philadelphia and graduated from Roman Catholic High School. In 1961 he received his Bachelor of Arts degree in history and English from Lincoln University in Pennsylvania, and was a recipient of the Eichelburger Award for Creative Writing from that school. After graduating from college, Neal taught creative writing, a course entitled “Afro-American Literature and Cultural History,” and other English courses at several universities including City College of New York, Case Western Reserve and Yale University between 1963 and 1976. In 1970 he was a recipient of a Guggenheim Fellowship for Afro-American critical studies. Graduate courses in folklore completed in 1964 at the University of Pennsylvania provided Neal with the opportunity to develop his writing skills, but it was folk tales, slang and street chants that shaped his distinctive style of poetry.
In 1964 Neal moved from Philadelphia where he had been teaching at Drexel Institute of Technology to New York City. The following year he married Evelyn Rodgers, a chemist at Mount Sinai Hospital; they adopted a boy, Avatar, in 1971. The Neal's residence on Jumel Terrace in the Sugar Hill section of Harlem, purchased in 1971, served as a magnet for the creative individuals of the period, particularly literary figures whose works gained attention during the late 1960's and the early 1970's, including Amiri Baraka (Leroi Jones), Ishamel Reed, Quincy Troupe, Askia Muhammad Toure, Hoyt Fuller, Stanley Crouch, and Henry Dumas. During this period, Neal worked as a copywriter for John Wiley and Sons (1964), and wrote for Liberator magazine, a progressive journal of that time and a publication for which he eventually became arts editor. During his Liberator period (1964-1966) he wrote accounts of cultural events and conducted interviews with writers, artists, and musicians.
Neal's commitment to radical politics was demonstrated through his position as education director of the Black Panther Party and as a member of the Revolutionary Action Movement, both in the 1960's. Baraka has written that he and Neal initially met at a demonstration protesting Patrice Lumumba's 1961 assassination. Neal's relationship with Baraka became more firmly established after Neal wrote an article entitled The Development of Leroi Jones which discussed Baraka's transformation from a Beat poet to a revolutionary artist. Together with Askia Toure, Neal and Baraka became principal movers in a group that created the Black Arts Repertory Theatre School in Harlem in 1964. They produced a number of plays including Jones' Jello and Dutchman, and also initiated a series of poetry readings and concerts. The Black Arts Theatre attacked the values of the Establishment theater in New York and presented art that reflected black life with its history of resistance and struggle. The theater was forced to close because of factionalism among the members and the cut of government funds (channeled through HARYOU-ACT) due to this theater's opposition to traditional theater and values. By now, however, the new direction forged in the theater became the impetus for the Black Arts Movement.
This movement by young black artists in the 1960's sought to create art forms that would advance black people's liberation. Neal described the Black Arts Movement as being radically opposed to any concept that alienates the artists from their community. Rather than fuse their ideas with the mainstream white culture, black writers, plastic artists and musicians should speak directly to the needs and aspirations of black America. Neal wrote that “Black Art is the aesthetic and spiritual sister of the Black Power concept.” Both related to the African-American's desire for self-determination and nationhood. According to Neal, Black Arts was concerned with the relationship between art and politics; Black Power with the art of politics. The Black Arts Movement proposed a separate symbolism, mythology, critique and iconology. Individuals whose perceptions and art work were associated with the movement knew that their perception of reality was different from that of the white American majority.
Neal's belief in the centrality of African-American music to developing a black aesthetic was expressed in essays he published in Negro Digest in 1966 and 1967. He, Baraka and A.B. Spellman also collaborated on a magazine, Cricket, a publication devoted to African-American music, which espoused a black nationalistic philosophy. Although Cricket ceased publication after three issues, it served as a vehicle through which black writers attempted to define black art forms and aesthetics.
In 1968 Neal and Baraka edited Black Fire: An Anthology of Afro-American Writing, a significant publication for the Black Arts Movement, and Neal wrote two ground breaking essays that sought to define the movement. Still the seminal anthology of that period, Black Fire contains works by well-known social critics, poets and playwrights such as James Boggs, Ed Bullins, Sonia Sanchez, Stokely Carmichael, John Henrik Clarke, Harold Cruse, Henry Dumas, and Hoyt Fuller.
In addition to writing essays concerning such topics as the arts and artists, Harlem, and the death of Malcolm X, Neal served as a literary and music critic, writing essays about the works of Ralph Ellison, Zora Neale Hurston, Charlie Parker, and others. Among his many projects, Neal was responsible for the publication of a new edition of Hurston's autobiography, Dust Tracks on a Road, and for her novel, Jonah's Gourd Vine, for which he wrote the introductions (1971).
Neal also published two books of poetry: Black Boogaloo(1969) and Hoodoo Hollerin' Bebop Ghosts(1974). Black Boogaloo focuses on discovering the historical moment when Africans lost their connection with their gods and ancestors, thereby losing themselves. Hoodoo Hollerin' Bebop Ghosts, Neal's second volume of poetry, explores black folk culture and figures, especially black liberation and Shine. His dramatic works include The Glorious Monster in the Bell of the Horn and In an Upstate Motel, both of which were performed during Neal's lifetime as well as after his death. Lesser known as an arts administrator, Neal held the position of Executive Director for the District of Columbia Commission on the Arts and Humanities (1976-1979), a city agency that made grants to artists and organizations that encouraged the development of the arts in black communities, including the Elma Louis School of Fine Arts in Roxbury, Massachusetts.
At his death of a heart attack at age forty-three, Neal was assisting the percussionist Max Roach to write his autobiography and had completed a jazz series for a Boston television station and a film script on musical improvisation for Clark College in Atlanta. Neal had nearly completed a book on the rise of black consciousness in the 1960's he had entitled New Space: Critical Essays on American Culture. This book, published posthumously as Visions of a Liberated Future: Black Arts Movement Writings: Larry Neal(New York, Thunder's Mouth Press, 1989) is a compilation of selected works by Neal (encompassing poetry, essays, and drama); many entries were published during his lifetime. Although not credited, Neal's widow Evelyn Neal assisted in the production of the book by selecting material that was included.
The Larry Neal Papers date from 1961 to 1985 and document Neal's role as writer/editor and seminal figure in the Black Arts Movement. The papers consist principally of manuscripts and research materials for Neal's diverse forms of writings, including essays, scripts, screenplays, poems, stories, and anthologies. Published copies of some of his writings are included in the collection, as are writings by colleagues. Neal's professional papers include correspondence with colleagues and publishers. Materials post-dating his death in 1981 document the various memorials and a conference honoring his achievements.
The collection is divided into six series and thirteen subseries. The titles, dates and box numbers are as follows:
Personal Papers, 1966-1985: Box 1
Professional Papers, 1966-1981: Box 2-5
Writings
Essays, 1970-1975: Box 6-8
Scripts, 1972-1980: Box 9-14
Screenplays, 1967-1979: Box 15-17
Screenplays, 1967-1979: Box 15-17
Poems, 1974-1979: Box 18-19
Anthologies and Other Publication Projects, 1961-1981: Box 20-23
Short Stories, 1973 & n.d.: Box 24-25
Interviews, 1973-1980: Box 26
Notes, 1971-1979: Box 29-30
D.C. Commission on the Arts and Humanities
Reference Materials
Subject File, 1965-1980: Box 31-36
Card File, n.d.: Box 37
Annotated Books, 1960-1978: Box 38-40
Writings by Other Authors
Essays, Short Stories, 1966-1979: Box 41-43
Scripts, 1972-1977: Box 44-45
Purchased from Evelyn L. Neal, 1986
SCM 86-32
Donated by Evelyn L. Neal, 1988
SCM 88-49
Donated by Evelyn L. Neal, 1990
SCM 90-17
The following items were removed from:
Name of Collection/Papers Larry Neal Papers MG 344
Accession Number SCM 86-32, SCM 88-49, SCM 90-17
Donor: Evelyn Neal
Date received: 1986, 1988, 1990
Date transferred: 1987, 1987, 1990
The item(s) listed below have been sent to the division indicated, either to be retained or disposed of there. Any items that should receive special disposition are clearly marked.
Schomburg Library:
2 R.C.'s of magazines - college press, local, national and international circulation periodicals, etc.
2 R.C.'s of books: small press, short publishing life, etc.
1 R.C of books: non-annotated; some autographed.
3 R.C. of annotated books - One box contains out-of-scope books.
Schomburg Art and Artifacts Division:
Thirteen art cards and small posters.
Schomburg Moving Image and Recorded Sound Division:
1 R.C. and one “shoebox” size plastic box of audiotapes, and one 16mm film, 23 cassettes, and 54 reels.
Schomburg Photographs and Print Division:
1/2 AB of photographs, contact sheets, and slides depicting Neal, family, and actors and of the Neal funeral.
Other:
Vertical File: One file folder of materials.
Archives: 1/2 R.C. of programs, playbills, and exhibit catalogs. Music books of Duke Ellington (2), Billie Holiday (1), Stevie Wonder (1), and sheet music for “In the Rain,” sheet music and additional music books for others.
Accessioned by: Janice Quinter
Date: 9/22/95
Harris, Norman, Larry Neal. Davis, Thadious M. and Trudier Harris, eds. Dictionary of Literary Biography. Vol. 38, Afro-American Writers After 1955: Dramatists and Prose Writers. Detroit, MI: Gale Research, 1985
Neal, Larry, The Black Arts Movement. Davis Thadious M. and Trudier Harris, eds. Dictionary of Literary Biography, vol. 38, Afro-American Writers After 1955: Dramatists and Prose Writers. Detroit, MI: Gale Research, 1985
Neal, Larry. Visions of a Liberated Future: Black Arts Movement Writings, Schwartz, Michael, ed. New York: Thunder's Mouth Press, 1989
Baraka, Amiri, 1934-; Ellison, Ralph; Fuller, Charles, 1939-; Fuller, Hoyt, 1923-1981; Hurston, Zora Neale; Nascimento, Abdias do, 1924-; Neal, Larry, 1937-; Parker, Charlie, 1920-1955; Reed, Ishmael, 1938-; Roach, Max, 1924-2007; Sackler, Howard; Schultz, Charles H; Viera de Silva, Antonio; Ward, Douglas Turner; Wright, Richard, 1908-1960; Black Panther Party; Congreso de la Cultura Negra de las America (1977): Columbia, South America); Congress of African Peoples; D.C. Commission on the Arts and Humanities; World Festival of Negro Arts; African American authors; African American dramatists; African American musicians; African American poets; African Americans -- Intellectual life; African Americans -- Music; African Americans -- Race identity; American drama -- African American authors; American literature -- African American authors; American poetry -- African American authors; Black arts movement; Revolutionary poetry; Riots; Riots -- California (Los Angeles); Riots -- Connecticut (New Haven); Riots -- Michigan (Detroit); Riots -- New Jersey (Newark); Riots -- New York (State) -- New York; Schomburg NEH Archival Resources for the Study of the Post-Civil Rights Movements Project; Manuscripts; Poems; Scripts
- Personal Papers
  The PERSONAL PAPERS series, 1966-1985 (.4 lin. ft.), is composed of biographical information including Neal's resumes, incoming letters, his marriage certificate, and photocopies of photographs of his family and colleagues (Schomburg Center's Photographs and Prints Division maintains a Larry Neal Photograph Collection). Most of this series deals with Neal's death in 1981, and includes letters of condolence, funeral (viewing) guest book, memorials, obituaries, literary criticism in the form of a memorial and a literary conference named in his honor, which was sponsored by the D.C. Commission on the Arts and Humanities.
  - Biographical Information/Resumes, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Personal Correspondence, 1969-1978 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Astrology, September 21, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Marriage Certificate, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Applications for Birth Certificate and Passport, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Music Notebook, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Financial Records, 1968-1978 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Photographs - Photocopies, 1972-1981 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Evelyn Neal, 1974-1976 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Death of Larry Neal
    - Funeral, Hospital, Insurance, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Letters of Condolence, January, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Letters of Condolence, Flower Cards, January-March (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Viewing-Guest Book, January, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Memorials, 1981-1985 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Obituaries, January, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Literary Criticism - The Mojo and the Sayso: Myth and Ritual in the Work of Larry Neal by Wesley Brown, November 14, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - D.C. Commission on the Arts and Humanities - Second Annual Larry Neal Writer's Conference, May 11-12, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Professional Papers
  The PROFESSIONAL PAPERS series, 1966-1981 (1.6 lin. ft.), includes letters from significant correspondents such as Amiri Baraka, Gwendolyn Brooks, Eddie Ellis, Hoyt Fuller, Langston Hughes, Woodie King, Dudley Randall, Max Roach, Leopold Sedar Senghor, and Chiz Schultz. Topics discussed in the correspondence include Neal's plans for projects involving music, writing, filming, and the production of plays he wrote as well as the Journal of Black Poetry. Avatar Enterprises, Neal's production company is represented by the incorporation book and related letters.
  As an instructor at various universities, the teaching materials, student papers, and administrative documents in the collection reflect this aspect of Neal's career. Correspondence with organizations in which he was involved include the Federal Theatre Project in the 1970's and 1980's. Addresses and datebooks complete the professional papers series.
  - Correspondence
    - 1966-1967 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - January-April (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - May-August (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - September-December (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - January-April (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - May-August (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - September-December (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - 1970 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - 1971 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - 1972 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - 1973 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - January-August (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - September-December (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - 1975 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - 1976 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - 1977 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - 1978 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Letter To the Editor, 1978 and n.d (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - 1979 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - 1980 (Box 3, Folder 4-5)
    - Oye Willie Writers' Guide, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - 1981 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - 1985 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - n.d (Box 3, Folder 9-10)
    - Journal of Black Poetry, 1967-1969 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Avatar Enterprises
    - 1971 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Incorporation Book, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Teaching
    - Diary - Excerpts, May 1968 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Brooklyn College, SEEK Program, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Teaching Materials, 1968-1980 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Yale University, 1971-1980 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Williams College, Colgate University, 1974-ca. 1980 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Student Papers
      - 1974-1979 (Box 4, Folder 2)
      - 1976 (Box 4, Folder 3)
      - n.d (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Class Lists, 1975-1979 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Lincoln University, 1979-1980 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Creative Writing Class - Craft of Writing, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Class Materials and Notes (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Permission for Reprints, 1967-1973 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Contracts, Agreements, 1968-1979 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Copyright Registrations, 1968-1976 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Guggenheim Fellow, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Screenplay Writer's Employment Agreement re 0 with Neal and Hoyt Fuller (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Federal Theatre Project, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Gordy Foundation Program Memorandum (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Langston Hughes Memorial Tribute - Program, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - National Center of Afro-American Artists, Elma Lewis School of Fine Arts, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - WNET - Proposal Submitted to National Endowment for the Humanities - “Celebrating Jazz,”, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Addresses, Business Cards, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Address Book, n.d, 1979 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Datebooks
    - 1967 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - 1970 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - 1975 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - 1976 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - 1979 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Travel Log, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Calendars
    - 1975 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - 1979 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - 1980-1981 (Box 5, Folder 11)
- Writings
  The largest series in this collection is Neal's WRITINGS, 1970-1975, (8.2 lin. ft.) and is divided into the genres in which he wrote.
  - Essays
    The Essays subseries, 1970-1975 (1 lin. ft.) encompasses literary criticism principally of black writers and themes for which Neal was well-known. The essays Neal intended to be included in New Space: Critical Essays on American Culture, published posthumously as Visions of a Liberated Future: Black Arts Movement Writings: Larry Neal, have been maintained under Neal's original title.
    - African Culture (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Any Day Now: Black Art and Black Liberation (Box 6, Folder 2-3)
    - Autobiographical Sketch - Incomplete (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - The Arts, Technology and Media - Incomplete (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - The Beatles is Comin' Out of a Different Bag (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Black Aesthetic (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Black Aesthetic/Writer's Theory (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - A Letter on the Black Aesthetic - Draft The Black Aesthetic and Ideological Imperative - Draft (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Black Aesthetic - Fragment (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - The Black Arts Movement (Box 6, Folder 11-12)
    - Black History/Cultural Development - Fragment (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Black Literature - Incomplete (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Black Poets - Incomplete (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Black Power in the International Scene (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Black Power/Liberation - Incomplete (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - Blind Tom - Incomplete (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - The Blues Regenerates a Man - Incomplete (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - Clarence Cooper, - Essay and Interview, October 7, 1967 (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - Claude Brown in the Promised Land Role of Black Writers, 1965 (Box 6, Folder 21)
    - Coming at You Weird - [Death of Malcolm X] (Box 6, Folder 22)
    - Conquest of The South (Box 6, Folder 23)
    - A Conversation With Piri Thomas (Box 6, Folder 24)
    - Cultural Conference - Notes: Guideline #One, 1978 (Box 6, Folder 25)
    - Cultural Nationalism and Black Theatre - Incomplete (Box 6, Folder 26)
    - Eatonville's Zora Neale Hurston: A Profile - Fragment (Box 6, Folder 27)
    - Ellison's Zoot Suit
      - Several Versions and Published Copy, 1970 (Box 6, Folder 28)
        - 1970 (Box 6, Folder 29)
        - Annotated, 1970 (Box 6, Folder 30)
    - Bird's Word, [About Charlie Parker], 1975 (Box 6, Folder 31)
    - The Idea of the Third World Black Power in the International Context - Nationalism, Pan-Africanism) (Box 6, Folder 32)
    - Introduction to the Black Arts Movement (Box 6, Folder 33)
    - Jonah's Vine Gourd (Zora Neale Hurston) - Notes for Introduction (Box 6, Folder 34)
    - Langston Hughes: Black America's Poet Laureate (Box 6, Folder 35)
    - The Mighty Wall - Fragment (Box 6, Folder 36)
    - Larry Neal on Malcolm X (For Rolling Stone) (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Leon Damas - Essay - Incomplete (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - A Nation of Flowers: A Black Aesthetic (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Nation Word, 1971 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Nation Word (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Note on the Artist, From Otto Rank's Art and Artist (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Notes on Afro-American Literature and the Class Struggle (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Notes on Marxism and Black Nationalism Impact on Black Arts Concepts (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - On the Significance of the Black Panther Party to the Nationalists (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Origin of Black Arts Movement (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - The Plot to Destroy Black Militancy (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Prologue: The Idea of Harlem (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Queen Mother - Incomplete (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Role of Black Writers - Questionnaire for Negro Digest Article (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - Separate State - Incomplete (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - [Sinner Man Where You Gonna Run To?] (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - The Sixties - Incomplete (Box 7, Folder 17)
    - Some Notes on a Magazine of Afro-American Popular Culture (Box 7, Folder 18)
    - Some Notes on Black Theatre in the Sixties (Box 7, Folder 19)
    - Spirits Rejoice: The Lowre Eastside and Black Art - Incomplete (Box 7, Folder 20)
    - Towards a Relevant Black Theatre (Box 7, Folder 21)
    - Towards the Destruction of the Western Poem - Incomplete (Box 7, Folder 22)
    - Tricks and Toys [for Liberator] (Box 7, Folder 23)
    - Visions of Harlem - Incomplete (Box 7, Folder 24)
    - The WESCAP Story (Box 7, Folder 25)
    - Notes for Essay (Box 7, Folder 26)
    - List of Essays (Box 7, Folder 27)
    - Review Essays
      - A Black Review of 'Sambo' (Box 7, Folder 28)
      - A Pitiful Answer to Doris Day, 1970
      - The Black Musician and White America: A Review of A.B. Spellman's Four Lives in the Bebop Business (Box 7, Folder 29)
      - The Free Southern Theater (Box 7, Folder 30)
      - Don't Let Your Bag Hang You Up (Box 7, Folder 31)
      - Douglas Turner Ward's 'The Reckoning': Born in a Barrel of Razor Blades (Box 7, Folder 32)
      - Drylongso: A Self Portrait of Black America (Box 7, Folder 33)
      - Long Live Blues People, The Beautiful Sun People - A Review/Essay on The Sound of Soul (Box 7, Folder 34)
      - Marvin Gaye (Box 7, Folder 35)
      - Mint Juleps and 'Black Revolution' - Review Essay (Box 7, Folder 36)
      - To Harlem With Love - [About Roy DeCarava, photographer] (Box 7, Folder 37)
      - Uptight, - Film Review (Box 7, Folder 38)
      - Essay Fragments (Box 8, Folder 1-7)
  - Scripts